Okay בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is ק"י, kuf
yud, 110.
And we pick up at the bottom of ק"ט עמוד ב'. kuf
tet amud bet. We had just gone through
different דרשות drashot to know that the order is first son, then
daughter, then father, and only then brother. And we had different ways
to learn that out. But and then we also importantly introduced the
idea that a man inherits from his wife from a special
דרשה drasha in the פסוקים. psukim. שאר, she'er, וקיים ליה u'kim li
שאר, הקרוב אליו, she'er hakarev elav, שאר זו אשתו. she'er zo ishto.
And then the גמרא Gemara introduced a very important idea that how
do we learn from the word, so the word
שאר she'er, הקרוב אליו, hakarev elav,
one דרשה drasha was that that was the father and that inserted
the father into the order. אליו, elav, whoops, הקרוב אליו, hakarev elav,
that inserted the father into the order and as we said, put
him even before the brothers. And the other one was that inserted
the wife. But then the גמרא Gemara says how do you know
שאר she'er is father? It quotes a פסוק pasuk שאר אביך, she'er
avicha, but it also שאר אמך, she'er imcha, even though that's not
פשט pshat of either of those פסוקים psukim anyway. And then introduced
a very important idea, which is what we left off, which is
משפחת האב קרויה משפחה, משפחת האם אינה קרויה משפחה, mishpachat ha'av koriya
mishpacha, mishpachat ha'em einah koriya mishpacha, which is really like, you know,
the as I said, the description of patriarchy, which is that a
family is defined by the father. All the children of the family
are of one family, children of a share even of different mothers,
you know, רחל, Rachel, לאה, Leah, etc. Children of the same mother
of different fathers are of different families. The family is defined by
the father and that's why the rules of the inheritance don't go,
if a person dies and there's no children, even after the father,
they don't go to the mother, because going to the mother is
going outside of the family. Right. So you know that and that
even more highlights the you know sort of the radicalness or you
know the way in which the בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad really disrupted
the patriarchy because because when a person dies, it goes to the
daughter, as we know. The daughter then marries somebody from a different
tribe, that is going to go outside of the family. Look, the
person could die, no sons, have a married daughter, and then it's
like already like, I mean, okay, the daughter owns it now, it's
not yet going to her husband or going to her son. Oh,
how about this example? A person has no sons, has a daughter,
the daughter married a man from a different tribe, the daughter died
and the daughter leaves behind a son. So he dies, you know
where it goes? It goes to his son of a different tribe.
Right. So that would be cases where in the death, it automatically,
not just eventually, automatically goes to a different tribe. Do people see
that? Because you know once your you go to everybody, right, this
was the rule I said, that you know first you go son,
if there's no son, then you know the son's children would sort
of you know be in the place of the son, but no
son and no children, daughter, and no daughter, before you go up
to the next level, you would go if the daughter has any
surviving children.
The son's daughter before the daughter, correct, and before the daughter's son,
yes, okay, so correct. They're seen as like replacements of that person,
you know, yes. So you could have a case a person dies
and it goes directly to a member of another tribe. So you
know the בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzelofchad, what they did was really radical.
It wasn't just, oh me as a girl I get a portion,
it's right, it's disruptive of the entire sort of tribal patriarchal structure
and keeping the land within the family estate. And the חידוש, chiddush,
or
not the חידוש, chiddush, so that's like the חידוש chiddush of בנות
צלפחד. Bnot Tzelofchad. And the גמרא Gemara sort of like saying however
you know that fundamental structure is still correct and therefore if a
person dies, it's not, it's you know it's one thing to go
to a daughter who at least is in some conceptual way, right,
a continuation of the person, even if that's going to mean it's
going to go to a different tribe, but it's not going to
go up to a mother because at the end of the day
he is part of his father's family and he is not part
of his mother's family. And the daughter at least until she married
out is part of her father's family. So it still stays, you
know we're maintaining still that fundamental idea of patriarchy and the family
defined by the father, yes.
So I think the Levites like intermarried in other
tribes, right?
But did everybody else intermarry in the tribes? Because that would mean
like the whole map of Israel.
Right, so that's exactly what, so practically, right, practically, exactly. So practically,
I'm sure it happened so pretty infrequently because people stayed within their
tribal lands, right, the same way, you know, so I'm sure before
the modern age of travel, you know, before the railroad, how often
did somebody from Montana marry somebody from New York, you know, you
stayed within your tribal lands. But in theory, yes, it could, there
was nothing restraining it, that was what the... That was what the
uncles of בנות צלפחד Bnot Tzelofchad said: they're going to marry some
other man and there's going to be sections of our thing that's
going to belong to a different
tribe, and משה Moshe said, okay, okay, they can't marry some other
men from a different tribe, but the גמרא Gemara says that that's
only for that generation, the גמרא Gemara quite, you know, which is
like, it's like, you know, it's amazing because that really would have
been a more maintaining of keeping things to, you know, within, if
not within the the the father's family, but within the tribe, and
the גמרא Gemara says that was only for that generation. So in
principle, you could have the land of יהודה Yehuda with this section
belonging to שמעון, Shimon, this section belonging to יששכר, Yissachar, this section
belonging to זבולון, Zevulun, but probably it happened only rarely, you know.
But of course there was the whole case about the פילגש בגבעה,
pilegesh b'Givah, right, where all the tribes דווקא davka made a point
of intermarrying, of marrying, you know, with the בנימינים. Binyamites. Anyway, so
that is the basic principle that the גמרא Gemara has said: משפחת
אב קרויה משפחה, משפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה, mishpachat av kruya mishpacha,
mishpachat em eina kruya mishpacha, but it led to a whole question
about this person who was involved in the פסל של מיכה, pesel
shel Micha, who said he was a לוי Levi from the family
of יהודה, Yehuda, which seemed to be that even though his fundamental
tribal identity was defined by his father, that at least at a
secondary level he was also recognized as belonging to his mother's family,
because from the לוי Levi from the tribe of יהודה. Yehuda. And
in the end the גמרא Gemara says that, I mean that's certainly
פשט pshat of the פסוקים, pesukim, from the family of יהודה, Yehuda,
but, yeah, but in the end the גמרא Gemara says fine, he
was a לוי, Levi, and it even says he was משה'ס Moshe's
grandson, so he certainly was a לוי, Levi, because משה Moshe was
a לוי. Levi. Why does it call him from the family of
יהודה? Yehuda? Not because he was really from the family of יהודה,
Yehuda, but to associate him with מנשה, Menashe, who wasn't going to
be around for a few hundred years yet, and who was an
idolater. Okay, so it gets out of it, but clearly that seems
like evidence that we're not completely forgetting the mother's family. Alright, so
now based on that, the associating this לוי Levi who served as
a priest in the temple of מיכה, Micha, מיכה'ס Micha's temple, I
bet we know it had an idol, it was to God, but
it still had an idol, and now saying that it was משה'ס
Moshe's grandson, the גמרא Gemara picks up in the following way. The
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי
יוחנן,
Amar
Rabbi
Yochanan, okay,
the first wide line, last word of the first wide line on
כט עמוד ב. Kaf-Tet amud Bet. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי: מכאן שתולין את הקלקלה במקולקל. Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi
Shimon ben Yochai: mikan shetolin et hakalkala bamkulkal.
Since it says that it associates him with the tribe of יהודה,
Yehuda, and it sort of uses the word also מנשה Menashe instead
of the word משה Moshe according to the גמרא'ס Gemara's דרשה, drasha,
to associate him with מנשה, Menashe, you see that you associate, you
know, somebody corrupt with with something that is corrupt, you know, even
though it's not technically actually related, you know, you you attribute, you
make those types of links. So let's, we'll see an example of
that. So you say he comes from יהודה Yehuda even though he
doesn't because because of the association with עבודה זרה. avoda zara. רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא אמר מהכא Rabbi Yossi be-Rabbi Chanina amar me-hacha from
here: וגם הוא טוב תואר מאד ואותו ילדה אחרי אבשלום. vegam hu
tov to'ar m'od ve'oto yalad acharei Avshalom. Okay,
this is אדוניה. Adoniyah. So it says אדוניה Adoniyah was very beautiful,
and she gave birth to him after אבשלום. Avshalom. So the גמרא
Gemara asks a very reasonable question. והלא אדוניה בן חגית? vahalo Adoniyah
ben Chagit? What do you mean? אדוניה'ס Adoniyah's mother was
חגית, Chagit, ואבשלום, ve'Avshalom, two sons of דוד, David, בן מעכה. ben
Maacha. So what does it mean she gave birth to him after
אבשלום? Avshalom? Of course it could mean she gave birth to him
after מעכה Maacha gave birth to אבשלום, Avshalom, but the simple sense
of the פסוק pasuk certainly implies that אבשלום Avshalom was her son
as well. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא מתוך שעשה מעשה אבשלום
דמרד במלכות, ela mitoch she'asa ma'aseh Avshalom d'marad bemalchut, since אדוניה Adoniyah
was similar to אבשלום Avshalom in that they both rebelled against the
king and against their father דוד, David, תלאו הכתוב באבשלום. tala'o hakatuv
be'Avshalom. The פסוק pasuk went out of the way to make an
association with אבשלום Avshalom even though it really wasn't relevant because it
sort of wants to say oh you're all birds of a feather,
you know. So it's תולים קלקלה במקולקל, tolin kalkala bamkulkal,
you go out of your way to make such associations even if
they're not really, like, you know, warranted, but because they're warranted because
of the sort of moral message involved, that they're all of a
similar type of a character. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, so
said רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, לעולם ידבק אדם בטובים, le'olam yidbak adam
betovim, a person should always cleave to good people. שהרי משה שנסע
בת יתו, sheharei Moshe shenasa bat Yitro, no matter how great you
are, you have to go out of your way to make sure
that you also keep company with good people, and here it's not
just keep company, it's also marry into the family of good people.
Okay, so let's because now we're going to deal with the obviously
the disturbing idea that משה'ס Moshe's grandson was as a priest to
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Again, I just want to be clear, it's
an idol that represents, that is in the worship of God, it's
not worship of other gods, but it still is obviously forbidden worship.
Okay, שהרי משה שנסע בת יתרו, sheharei Moshe shenasa bat Yitro, משה
Moshe married the daughter of יתרו, Yitro, יצא ממנו יהונתן. yatza mimenu
Yehonatan. So he, his grandson was this יהונתן Yehonatan who was a
priest to the פסל של מיכה. pesel shel Micha. ואהרן שנסע בת
עמינדב, ve-Aharon shenasa bat Aminadav, אהרן Aharon who married the daughter of
עמינדב, Aminadav, יצא ממנו פנחס. yatza mimenu Pinchas. פינחס Pinchas came out
of him who
was like anyway nowadays so to say is that zealousness that violent
zealousness is that appropriate? But obviously the in the the פסוקים pesukim
obviously בקנאו את קנאתי bekano es kinasi he did this amazing thing
defending God's honor. So that was because he now of course the
funny thing here is that יתרו Yisro well first of all אהרן
Aharon did the עגל egel well maybe that's a good point I
hadn't even thought about that but look at that even if you
yourself did the עגל egel if you marry the daughter of a
good man your kids are going to turn out okay but משה
רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu right who spoke פנים אל פנים panim el panim
to God right he look what happened because of that. So that's
a good point I didn't even think about that irony. Anyway but
the funny thing of course is that יתרו Yisro is not טובים
tovim I mean יתרו Yisro recognizes
God יתרו Yisro comes right says וישמע יתרו כהן מדין vayishma Yisro
kohen Midyan etc. but of course because he's כהן מדין kohen Midyan
and he's a priest and presumably the priests there was if you
weren't a Jew or whatever weren't from בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael they
were priests to
עבודה זרה avodah zarah so that's a bit of why wouldn't we
say that he abandoned that and he recognized God but anyway it's
very interesting that the גמרא Gemara sees יתרו Yisro as not טובים.
tovim. The other thing that is very interesting about this is and
it's going to become even sharper in a few minutes is that
in the context of discussing בנות יתרו Bnos Yisro right and about
how not בנות יתרו Bnos Yisro sorry בנות צלפחד Bnos Tzelofchad and
how that sort of disrupts the patriarchal
structure right so here it's interesting because we're now sort of focusing
when a man marries a woman we're focusing on the men. Whose
daughter did he marry? Right so if you married יתרו's Yisro daughter
right and then what is the son going to come out to
be or the grandson come out to be so almost like the
woman becomes like invisible right in that equation right so אהרן Aharon
who marries עמינדב's Aminadav daughter his son or his grandson a grandson
is פינחס. Pinchas. Right so it's still the men and the men
and the men right and the women almost become invisible. You marry
this person this man's daughter so your grandson turns out this way.
You marry this man's daughter your grandson turns out that way. So
in a way that's right really sort of reinstating a very strong
sort of patriarchal perspective.
That's good for the women she wants to be married to someone
good reverse that logic. Exactly. Right now means that people questionable whatever
characteristics will stick with each other.
Right I understand yeah.
But there was this thing coming up of דבורה. Devorah.
I'm going to get there right right we're going to get there
exactly. דבורה Devorah and צפורה. Tzipporah.
דבורה Devorah and
then later on. Yeah no I'm just saying was she married did
she
have did anybody know she was divorced. No I mean it's true
obviously we had strong women leaders and
strong whatever strong women
figures right but but here look also so much I mean remember
there was a גמרא Gemara before where they were trying to name
the unnamed women
in the תנ"ך Tanakh I don't know if you were there right
who was נח's Noach wife who was whatever so obviously there sometimes
are named and strong women who are characters in themselves but often
not right often it's sort of the men. So all right so
the
גמרא Gemara says like this okay ופינחס לא מיתרו אתי uPinchas lo
miYisro asi
wait
a minute that doesn't make sense because פינחס Pinchas also descended from
יתרו. Yisro. How do you know? והכתיב ואלעזר בן
אהרן לקח לו מבנות פוטיאל לו לאשה. ve-haksiv ve-Elazar ben Aharon lakach
lo mi-bnos Putiel lo le-isha. אלעזר Elazar sorry אהרן's Aharon son right
אהרן Aharon married the daughter of עמינדב Aminadav but אלעזר Elazar married
the daughter from the daughters of פוטיאל. Putiel. So who are the
daughters of
פוטיאל? Putiel? מאי לאו דאתי מיתרו שפיטם עגלים לעבודה זרה mai lav
de-asi mi-Yisro she-pitem agalim le-avodah zarah so there's a classic דרשה drasha
that אלעזר Elazar married a daughter of יתרו Yisro following משה's Moshe
example and why is יתרו Yisro called פוטיאל? Putiel? So again emphasizing
his עבודה זרה avodah zarah association not his positive association because he
fattened calves for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So look at that and
even with that פינחס Pinchas was the product of that. לא דאתי
מיוסף שפטפט ביצרו lo de-asi mi-Yosef she-pitpeit be-yitzro no no no פוטיאל
Putiel is a we're going to go by the different דרשה drasha
of פוטיאל. Putiel. אלעזר Elazar married a daughter of יוסף Yosef and
יוסף Yosef was פוטיאל Putiel because he שפטפט pitpeit he like combated
his יצר הרע yetzer hara when he was tempted by אשת פוטיפר.
eshes Potiphar. So the גמרא Gemara says no no you can't say
that. We have a good like our classic approach here is to
see that פינחס Pinchas was a descendant of יתרו. Yisro. והלא שבטים
מבזים אותו ve-halo shevatim mevazim oso you know our sort of מדרש
midrash but that we
really like we're not going to debate this
מדרש midrash our the מדרש midrash that we hold is that the
tribes mocked יתרו Yisro or degraded him. ואומרים ראיתם בן פוטי זה
שפיטם אבי אמו עגלים לעבודה זרה יהרוג נשיא שבט מישראל ve-omrim re-ishem
ben Puti ze she-pitem avi imo agalim le-avodah zarah yahrog nesi shevet
mi-Yisrael excuse me ראיתם בן פוטי זה שפיטם re-ishem ben Puti ze
she-pitem excuse me שפיטם אבי אמו she-pitem avi imo עגלים לעבודה זרה
agalim le-avodah zarah יהרוג נשיא שבט מישראל yahrog nesi shevet mi-Yisrael who
is this guy this פינחס Pinchas his grandma what his mother's father,
his
grandfather was an idolater and he thinks that he has the right
to go ahead and kill a leader of a נשיא nasi of
a leader of the tribe of Israel? So we don't want to
sort of deny that
מדרש Midrash that אלעזר, Elazar, that אלעזר Elazar married a daughter of
יתרו. Yitro. So if אלעזר Elazar and that פנחס Pinchas was a
descendant of that, so
פנחס's Pinchas grandfather was an idolater, right? So it's so and nevertheless,
right, so how can you therefore compare and say look, פנחס Pinchas
derived from this line because they didn't marry into idolaters and משה's
Moshe grandson was an idolater because he married into a family that
the father was an idolater. פנחס's Pinchas also grandfather was an idolater.
So the גמרא Gemara says
no. אלא אי אבוה דאימיה מיוסף, אימיה דאימיה מיתרו. Ela ei avua
de'imei miYosef, imei de'imei miYitro. Fine. So פנחס Pinchas yes, it's both
פוטיאל Putiel means both יוסף Yosef and
יתרו. Yitro. So אלעזר Elazar married, married a descendant who is both
a descendant of יוסף Yosef and a descendant of יתרו. Yitro. One
way or the other, either his mother's father was from יוסף Yosef
and his mother's mother was from יתרו, Yitro, or
אי אבוה דאימיה מיתרו, אימיה דאימיה מיוסף, ei avuah de'imei miYitro, imei
de'imei miYosef, or his mother's father was from יתרו Yitro and his
mother's mother was from יוסף. Yosef. So
פוטיאל Putiel is אלעזר's Elazar wife descended both from יוסף Yosef and
from יתרו. Yitro. דיקא נמי דכתיב, Deika nami dechtiv, that's also can
be inferred from the reading of the from the close reading of
the פסוק. pasuk. Well, okay, one minute, because it says מבנות פוטיאל.
mibnot Putiel. תרתי. Tarti. So it doesn't say, it says it could
have said מבנות פוטל mibnot Putel or something maybe, right. פוטיאל Putiel
means two descendants, הפיטם hapitem מיתרו Yitro and המפטם עגלים לעבודה זרה.
ham'pitem agalim la'avodah zarah. שמע מינה, Shma mina, that's a good proof.
So of course Michael still says but okay, but you still have
פנחס Pinchas who one grand according to this, one grandfather was יתרו
Yitro and one grandfather
was, what do you call it, was יוסף, Yosef, and פנחס Pinchas
came out okay. So
משה, Moshe, so how is that different than משה's Moshe grandfather, right,
who descended
from whose, I guess, yeah
משה's Moshe grandson was the priest of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, his
great-grandfather was יתרו. Yitro. So still, how does it support the
argument, he פנחס Pinchas still came out okay and he didn't come
out
okay? So תוספות Tosafot and the רשב״ם Rashbam try to figure it
out, maybe because the יוסף Yosef counterbalances it, maybe because the גמרא
Gemara says maybe this means like he was, אלעזר Elazar married
a somebody who was a
great-great-granddaughter, or a great-granddaughter, not that it was just, it was more
generations removed. Okay, but somehow it's not as clean as it was
before. What did you want to say? Alright, so anyway somehow we've
still got this, we can't make that clean
דרשה, drasha, look what happened, משה Moshe married into a family of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah look what happened to his son, אהרן Aharon
didn't marry into such a family and פנחס Pinchas turned and look
what, and his grandson came out okay, it's a little more complicated
than that. But nevertheless, we're still maintaining that argument. Okay, אמר רבא.
Amar Rava. So now that was about marrying in,
about how's your grandson going to turn out based on what man's
daughter you marry. So now the גמרא Gemara brings in a focus
about not which man's daughter you marry but
who's the brother of the woman you marry. אמר רבא הנושא אשה
צריך
שיבדוק באחיה. Amar Rava: hanosei ishah tzarich sheyivdok be'acheiha. Okay, we've already
had ידבק, yidbak, you have to cleave to good people, here it
says you have to be בודק, bodek, you have to check out
her brothers. שנאמר ויקח אהרן את אלישבע בת עמינדב אחות נחשון. Shene'emar:
vayikach Aharon et Elisheva bat Aminadav achot Nachshon. אהרן Aharon took אלישבע
Elisheva the daughter of עמינדב, Aminadav, so before we were focusing on
marrying into the family of עמינדב Aminadav and now we're focusing on
that the sister of נחשון Nachshon who was the head of the
tribe of יהודה. Yehudah. ממשמע שנאמר בת עמינדב איני יודע שאחות נחשון
היא? Mimasma shene'emar bat Aminadav eini yodea she'achot Nachshon hi? Right, if
she's the daughter of עמינדב Aminadav I know that she's the sister
of נחשון. Nachshon. מה תלמוד לומר אחות נחשון? Mah talmud lomar achot
Nachshon? So why did it say the sister of נחשון? Nachshon? מכאן
שהנושא אשה צריך שיבדוק
באחיה. Mikan shehanosei ishah tzarich sheyivdok be'acheiha. So we already knew he
was marrying into a good family because of the father, but he
also just to be careful, sure, you want to check out the
brother. Now what are you going to learn out from the brother
that you're not knowing from being part of the father? So it
says תנא רוב בנים דומים לאחי האם. Tana: rov banim domim le'achei
ha'em.
Most of the sons of a woman will be similar to her
brother or brothers. So if you want to know what your sons
are going to be like, check out your wife's brothers. Now you
could sort of argue that the logic of that is that your
wife will raise your kids the same way her mother raised her
kids, so if you want to see
how her sons are going to turn out, look at how her
mother's sons. turned out, just sort of see that if you sort
of base it on raising? I mean, or you could just base
it on genes. She's sort of the genes that are going to
lead to certain types of boys, what types of boys are you
going to have as a result of marrying this woman? Of course
the funny thing is, if you want to see how somebody is
raised, or you want to see how good their genes are, whatever
it is, that's the woman you're marrying. The woman you're marrying, she's
a wonderful woman, she was raised well, she has all these מידות,
middos, these מעלות, mailos, so oh, that's how your kids are going
to turn out. But then again, the interesting thing is, is that
like the girls don't matter here, right? It's about the boys. How
are your boys going to turn out? And therefore you want to
look at her brothers. So it becomes again very interesting. You're marrying
this woman, but your interest is in your sons and your grandsons,
and you look at her father and her
brothers. So this these גמרות Gemaras are really like very much sort
of restoring that sort of very patriarchal look. And again, in a
way counterbalancing the way in which בנות צלפחד Bnos Tzelofchad really disrupted
that patriarchy and made the women's really a part of that family
and ones that could even take the נחלה nachala and bring it
to a different שבט. shevet. Okay, but this becomes very interesting that
you're looking at the father and at the brother if you want
to figure out what's going to be the children, not directly at
the woman. Yes, מיכל. Michal. רות, Ruth, right.
Yeah.
Or her brothers, sisters?
Exactly. Exactly. So yeah, I obviously there are very good I mean
it's like the point before about
דבורה, Devorah, these are good counterexamples to this. No, right, but the
point is like we don't care about her father right your point
is like רות Ruth ממש mamash like they were עובדי עבודה זרה,
ovdei avodah zarah, and right, and the great-grandchild was דוד המלך. David
HaMelech. That's an excellent point, right, exactly, exactly. So you're right, I
mean, thank you for that. That's obviously a bit of a curveball.
Yes, or go back to
early בראשית Bereishis to know that siblings don't always
turn out right, right, exactly. Are you talking about עשו ויעקב? Eisav
and Yaakov?
Right, exactly. All right, what are you confusing us with the facts?
Anyway. Or it could be just
getting to the frame, it could be, it makes you think something
even simpler that it'll be family gatherings, the boys will be with
their uncles, males
and toys, right, the male role models. Right. Okay. Yes.
I don't remember exactly but I think in like maybe somebody knows
like old or maybe still Arabic tradition, you can a girl can
marry her father's brother, but not the mother's brother. Like a closer
feeling
or something.
So you know that's interesting because I was
someone else was
telling me that in right yeah yeah no no no what do
you want to say
you see it like all as whatever anti-women or this they try
to explain something that's unexplainable and so they try to find proof
and I think they already know it's only going to go as
far as it goes right right right so I do think I
was someone else was telling me
that similar to
what מיכל Michal just said which is that
in matriarchies,
the men would still be the heads of the family but the
families would be defined through exactly משפחת אם, mishpachas em, how are
you related through the mother. But which man would be the head
of the family? It wouldn't because you only would associate relationships of
people that were related so it wouldn't be the mother's
husband because part of the whole problem of the whole reason of
matriarchies is you don't really know who the father is. So the
head of the family would be the mother's maternal brother. Right, because
then you know that they're all
related, because anyway, and you sort of see that by
רחל ולאה Rachel and Leah by רבקה Rivka where לבן, Lavan, right,
is has more of a stronger voice than בתואל, Besuel, than the
father. Anyway, so that maybe part of this about this actually דווקא
davka is reflecting a somewhat of a matriarchal view, focusing on the
mother's brother, of course the גמרא Gemara doesn't, okay, but it's possible.
It's possible. But I still think the net effect is that it
becomes very interesting, you're looking at all the male men of the
family and it's a focus on sons while you're marrying this woman.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. תנא, Tanna, we
taught.
רוב rov oh we just did that. ויסורו Vayasuru now this is
back to the פסוקים pesukim of the פסל pesel of מיכה, Micha,
so it says ויסורו שם ויאמרו Vayasuru sham vayomeru it's quoted a
little incorrectly here, ויסורו שם ויאמרו מי הביאך הלום. Vayasuru sham vayomeru
mi hevi'acha halom. So when the Danites came to the house of
מיכה Micha and they found this לוי, Levi, they said to him
who brought you here? ומה אתה עושה בזה, Umah atah oseh bazeh,
what are you doing? ומה לך פה, Umah lecha poh, what why
are you here? And he said, I'm a לוי Levi and I
was traveling through and I decided to come ahead and work for
this guy and be his priest for this פסל. pesel. So now
the דרשות derashos are the following because remember, he's a grandson of
משה. Moshe. So that's still like a bone in our craw, like,
you know, we have to deal with this, that this is a
grandson of משה. Moshe. So אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to
him, לאו ממשה קא אתית? lav mi'Moshe ka'atit? I don't understand. Are
you, are you a descendant of משה? Moshe? דכתיב אל תקרב הלום,
d'chtiv al tikrav halom, right, don't draw nigh, so מי הביאך הלום,
mi hevi'acha halom, right, we're hearing these echoes, right? So, you know,
who brought you? You're drawing close to עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Your
grandfather wouldn't come close, you know, to the, you know, to the,
what do you call it, to the סנה. sneh. So לאו ממשה
קא אתית? lav mi'Moshe ka'atit? I don't understand, didn't you come from
משה? Moshe? דכתיב מה זה בידך? d'chtiv ma zeh b'yadecha? בידך, b'yadecha,
excuse me. So it says ומה אתה עושה בזה? u'ma ata oseh
ba'zeh? מה זה? ma zeh? מה אתה? ma ata? So, so you
know, what's, what's going on here? לאו ממשה קא אתית? lav mi'Moshe
ka'atit? Didn't you come from משה? Moshe? דכתיב ואתה פה עמוד עמדי?
d'chtiv v'ata poh amod imadi? And it says ומה לך פה, u'ma
lecha poh, right? So משה Moshe had all these, you know, all
these echoes of משה Moshe who had all this closeness together. And
what are you doing being עובד עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah here?
So תעשה כהן לעבודה זרה? ta'aseh kohen l'avodah zarah? אמר להם, amar
lahem, he said back to them. What? Who are they speaking to?
They're speaking to, these are the, these are the Danites speaking to
the משה's, Moshe according to the מדרש, Midrash, משה's Moshe grandson who
was the, who served in the, to the, as the כהן kohen
for the פסל מיכה. pesel Micha. So אמר להם, amar lahem, he
said to them, כך מקובלני מבית אבי אבא, kach mekubalni mibeit avi
aba, this is the tradition I have from my grandfather's house, meaning
משה: Moshe: לעולם ישכיר אדם עצמו לעבודה זרה ואל יצטרך לבריות. l'olam
yaskir adam atzmo l'avodah zarah v'al yetztarech labriyot. You should sooner hire
yourself out to, literally, to
idolatry, rather than act having to beg, having to be supported by
people. If, it's so important, you know, self-sufficiency, earning your own living,
that before you went ahead and took צדקה tzedakah from other people,
or you know, it's better to take any job, even if it
means working in a house of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Now, even
in that context, you could say ישכיר אדם עצמו לעבודה זרה yaskir
adam atzmo l'avodah zarah means I'm going to hire myself out to
this temple to mow the lawn, to chop the wood, you know?
It doesn't, right, exactly. It doesn't mean that I'm actually going to
worship עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, right? Hiring yourself out to people of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah or a house of עבודה זרה avodah zarah
is still different than actually being a כהן לעבודה זרה. kohen l'avodah
zarah. But anyway, but it's also a very powerful statement in חז"ל
Chazal about like how much we have to, you know, about the
importance of like earning your own living and what that does for
dignity and, you know, and so on and how significant that is.
Right, exactly. Self-reliance, exactly. So who, so now, but is that really
the teaching from משה רבינו? Moshe Rabbeinu? By the way, this is
very much is,
reflects the פסוקים psukim because the פסוקים psukim there in this story
make it clear that he was, you know, looking to earn a
living, okay, that he was doing this because he was attracted, actually
מיכה Micha says to him, "I'll give you a lot of money,
I'll pay you a good salary." This is in the פסוקים, psukim,
okay? So it makes it clear that he's doing this for the
salary.
Remnant. ואל יצטרך לבריות. v'al yetztarech labriyot. So מר Mar says, והוא
סבר, v'hu savar, now this is a great ending of the גמרא.
Gemara. לעבודה זרה ממש. l'avodah zarah mamash. He misunderstood משה's Moshe teaching
because he thought it meant to really to idolatry. ולא היא, v'lo
hi, but that's not the case. אלא עבודה זרה ela avodah zarah
means עבודה שזרה לו. avodah she'zarah lo. Means a, right,
take any job, take something that is completely not natural to you,
but it's, right, but it doesn't really
mean... All out, you've got to, you've got
to, okay. Okay, but, but, but it doesn't mean, but anyway, but
even some, so it's a very obviously, you know, it's a cute
play on the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It actually reminds me of
the fact that like, somebody was telling me once, you know, that
when Israel was dealing with this whole issue about, about foreign workers,
you know, there was some, there was some like headline about something
like about עובדים זרים, ovdim zarim, or, which is the word in
Israel for foreign workers, right, foreign laborers, or, you know, anyway, somehow
got translated in the press as idolatry, as עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Anyway, yes, what did you want to say, Shana?
I was going to say it's also like a cautionary tale about
like what you say around your children or like because kids can
take things very literal when you mean it figuratively.
Aha, that's a good point. And maybe... you can't be saying so
much. And also, that the, and yeah, also by the way, going
back to the idea that the, you know, משה Moshe married into
a family of
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So don't say עבודה זרה avodah zarah in
that context where people think it means real עבודה זרה avodah zarah
where it could be real misunderstood.
Okay, כדאמר ליה רב לרב כהנא, k'd'amar leh Rav l'Rav Kahana, like
רב Rav said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, נטוש נבילתא בשוקא, nitosh
nevielta beshuka, you should prepare to actually flay a carcass, an animal
carcass even out in public. You know, get, take a job that
you feel is extremely demeaning. Here you are, you know, dealing with
dead animals, flaying the carcass, you know, and doing it in the,
and doing it in the... and doing it in the public, ושקול
אגרא, ushkol agra, and take your fee, ולא תימא גברא רבא אנא,
velo teima gavra raba ana, don't say, oh, this is beneath me,
I'm such an important person, וזילא בי מילתא, vezeila bei milta, and
this is
degrading. No,
it is more self-respecting to do a job and earn your keep
even if the work
might be repulsive than it would be to have to actually be
dependent upon other people. Now there's an interesting statement here which is,
first of all, some have the גרסא girsa ולא תימא כהנא אנא.
velo teima kahana ana. Don't say I'm a כהן, kohen, which actually
would be directly connecting to the whole story there because this guy,
well, he was a לוי Levi but serving as a כהן, kohen,
but even as a כהן, kohen, right, so don't say oh I'm
a כהן, kohen, how should I, who's a כהן kohen chosen to
serve God, go ahead and strip this carcass? Actually it's טומאה tumah
as well, it's not טומאה tumah that's forbidden to a כהן, kohen,
but the funny thing is because this was רב Rav talking to
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, but then תוספות Tosafot says there's a problem
though because there's evidence that רב כהנא Rav Kahana was not a
כהן. kohen. So what does it mean don't say oh I'm a
כהן kohen I can't do this? So תוספות Tosafot says maybe if
you have that גרסא girsa it's just like the earlier גמרא, Gemara,
just like the earlier גמרא, Gemara, remember what the גמרא Gemara said
that this guy was a לוי Levi and it said oh he
wasn't really a לוי, Levi, his name was לוי? Levi? So תוספות
Tosafot says the same thing here, don't say my name is רב
כהנא, Rav Kahana, I am the important רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, how
can I degrade myself? It's very cute, it's talking about the name
כהנא Kahana or the being of the כהן. kohen. But anyway, you
should be more prepared to do this than to actually have
to take support from others. Yes, Michael.
The interesting thing is if you contrast this to a מצוה זקן
ואינו לפי כבודו, mitzvah zaken ve'eino lefi kevodo, like אבידה, aveidah, you
don't have to return it. So you should take any degrading work
even if it's beneath your dignity, but you don't have to do
the same thing for a מצוה. mitzvah. I just find that very
interesting, but I guess that's the power of work.
Right, but
it's because the choice here is not a one-time thing either, also
the choice here is because it's a general sort of being self-sufficient
or being regularly on the, in general, it's not like saying, I
don't think the גמרא Gemara here is talking about a one-time thing.
If I'm right now I really am having a cash flow
problem and can I go to you and ask you for a
loan or whatever it is, I need, or whatever I'm out of
work now for the next week until some opportunity opens up, can
I get some support from you? I don't think that's the context
of the גמרא. Gemara. I need to tie me over until that
time. I think the context of the גמרא Gemara is
like it's either you're going to get a job or you're going
to regularly be supported by others. But the רשב"ם Rashbam illustrates this
well, if you look at the first sort of medium line of
the רשב"ם, Rashbam, וטול אגרא, utol agra, כלומר השתכר בשכר בשוק, klomar
hishtaker beschar bashuk, be willing to be paid for, take a fee
לעין כל, le'ein kol, ואין כאן חילול השם כלל, ve'ein kan chillul
Hashem klal, don't say oh my gosh it's a חילול השם, chillul
Hashem, a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham doing this type of work,
shoveling manure, picking up the trash. He says ולא קרינא ביה ומשנאי
אהבו מות, velo karina bei umasana'ei ahavu mavet,
those who cause me to be hated love death, דדרשינן ליה במסכת
שבת בתלמידי חכמים, dedarshinan lei beMasechet Shabbat betalmidei chachamim, we learn this
in מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbat by תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim שכתב רבב
על בגדו, shekatav revav al bigdo, if you're a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham and you're wearing stained clothing, you cause people to degrade religion,
degrade God. This is what a representative of God looks like, and
so on. And so normally we say that. אבל לעשות מלאכה להתפרנס
אין כאן גנאי. aval la'asot melacha lehitparnes ein kan genai.
That's okay how do you appear, but what things you have to
do to earn a living, there's nothing that, work,
there is nothing to be embarrassed about about what you have to
do to earn a living.
What's,
yeah. Do you need to step out, you okay?
Yeah, I'm okay.
All right. All right. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. All right, last point about this אגדתא agadata and then
we'll get back
to the more standard discussions of inheritance. Okay, okay. כיון דחזא דוד
דממונא חביב עליה ביותר, keivan dechaza David demamona chaviv aleih beyoter,
now
since דוד David saw that this grandson of משה Moshe was
so much wanted, was so willing to,
for the sake of money, and it was so money was so
dear to him, so מינהו על האוצרות, minahu al ha'otzarot, he decided
that I'm going to therefore take you away from this work of
working in the house of עבודה זרה avodah zarah and I'll appoint
you to be over my storehouses, my treasure houses, which you could
wonder somebody that runs after money in order to do עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, you really want to trust him to do your account?
שנאמר ושבואל בן גרשום בן משה. shene'emar uShevuel ben Gershom ben Moshe.
Okay,
so this is a פסוק pasuk in דברי הימים, Divrei HaYamim, not
מנשה, Menashe, משה. Moshe. So again it's the בן גרשום בן משה
ben Gershom ben Moshe and we before we had מנשה Menashe but
we said it was משה. Moshe. So we're associating this with the
same person, it's not necessarily פשט pshat that it's the same person,
but we're associating it with the same person. This is the grandson
of
משה, Moshe, ושבואל בן משה, uShevuel ben Moshe, מהו מנשה? mahu Menashe?
I know, you look at the side, the פסוק pasuk is משה.
Moshe. נגיד. Nagid. נגיד על האוצרות Nagid al ha'otzarot was the supervisor
over the storehouses. וכי שמואל שמו ולא יהונתן שמו, V'chi Shmuel shemo
v'lo Yehonatan shemo, so we're associating it with the same person because
once we make one of them the son of, you know, if
that was the grandson of משה, Moshe, the son of גרשום, Gershom,
so this is also the same. So אמר רב יוחנן ששב לאל
בכל לבו. Amar Rav Yochanan sheshav l'El bechol libo. Ah, he did
תשובה. tshuva. So it's שבואל. Shevuel. So we can't leave it that
משה's Moshe's grandson was a כהן לעבודה זרה. kohen l'avodah zarah. So
we have to say that he finally did תשובה. tshuva. He did
תשובה tshuva to abandon עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, not to abandon his
need for earning a nice living, so דוד Dovid still had to
give him this job. But enough maybe money turned him around, but
enough that he could trust him to be over the warehouses, the
storehouses. Now of course the רשב"ם Rashbam says the problem is that
the פסוקים psukim in שמואל Shmuel say that his descendants remained כהנים
kohanim for this פסל pesel of מיכה Micha until the exile of
the people of ישראל Israel from the land. So how do you
say that דוד Dovid took him away from that job? So he
says with the ירושלמי Yerushalmi asks the question and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
says, first of all דוד Dovid was also many generations after, so
we've got this guy living hundreds of years but okay, whatever. Anyway,
so the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says, so the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says once שלמה
המלך Shlomo HaMelech came in, he changed all of the staff.
He fired everybody and he hired a whole new staff. So then
this guy went back to
מיכה's Micha's בית עבודה זרה beis avodah zarah there. So I guess
his תשובה tshuva did not last too long. Alright anyway,
you got a new president, you got a whole new
staff. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, והבנים
את האב, v'habanim es ha'av, back to the
משנה. mishna. So the father inherits from the sons, that was the
חידוש chiddush introducing the father. But the sons inherit from the father,
that's like obvious. Okay but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara wants to make
it even more explicit. So מנלן? minalan? How do you know sons
inherit from father? דכתיב איש כי ימות ובן אין לו והעברתם את
נחלתו לבתו. Dechesiv ish ki yamut uven ein lo v'ha'avartem es nachalato
levito.
If he dies and no son, you pass it over to the
daughter. Which means when there is a son, the son gets first.
Okay, טעמא דאין לו בן, ta'ama d'ein lo ben, the reason the
daughter gets it is there's no son. הא יש לו בן בן
קודם, ha yesh lo ben ben kodem, the son comes first. So
אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye, so רב
פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי, Abaye, אימא, eima, wait, I have
a different way of reading the פסוק. pasuk. אי איכא בן ליראת
בן, i ika ben leyaras ben,
if there's a son, the son inherits. אי איכא בת ליראת בת,
i ika bas leyaras bas, if there's a daughter and not a
son, the daughter inherits. אי איכא בן ובת, i ika ben uvas,
maybe if there's a son and a daughter, לא האי ליראת ולא
האי ליראת, lo hai leyaras v'lo hai leyaras, neither of them will
inherit, meaning if a person dies, if there's only a son, the
son gets it. If he dies and there's no son and only
a daughter, the daughter gets it. But how do you know if
there's a son and a daughter, that the son gets it? So
of course like what? The גמרא Gemara says אלא למאן, ella l'man,
אלא למאן ליראת, ella l'man leyaras, אתו בר קשיי דמצי ליראת? asu
bar kashya de matza leyaras? Who,
so who do you want to inherit if there's a son and
a daughter? Do you want maybe the head of the city to
inherit, like you know the state will take it over? I mean
what? Somehow
בר קשיי bar kashya means the head of the city, like מושל
העיר. moshel ha'ir. Is I don't know, anyway, so obviously that's not
a read of a פסוק. pasuk. So הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, no
no no, this is how I meant I wanted to read the
פסוק. pasuk. אי איכא בן ובת, i ika ben uvas, לא האי
ליראת כולי ולא האי ליראת כולי. lo hai leyaras kulei v'lo hai
leyaras kulei. Maybe in that case it wouldn't all go to the
son, it certainly wouldn't all go to the daughter, and maybe it
wouldn't all go to the son. אלא כי הדדי ליראת, ella ki
hadadi leyaras, maybe they split it equally. Meaning maybe the פסוק pasuk
is saying like this: a son and a daughter are equal heirs.
So if a person dies and there's no son and only daughter,
the daughter is the daughter gets it. If there's no daughters and
only sons, the sons get it. If there's sons and daughters, the
sons and daughters get it. How do you read the פסוקים psukim
that the son comes
that if there's sons and daughters all goes to the son? Now
of course the point is because then the פסוק pasuk would just
say that you know if a person dies his inheritance passes over
to his children. And if there's no children it goes to the
brother. You wouldn't have to say if there's no son it goes
to the daughter, right? Why are you saying that if they're all
equal? Which is what the גמרא Gemara then asks. The גמרא Gemara
says אמר ליה אביי ואיצטריך קרא לאשמועינן, amar lei Abaye v'itzrecha kra
l'ashmiunan, היכא
דליכא אלא חד ברא לירתינהו לכולהו נכסי? heicha d'leisa ella chad bra
leyarsinu l'chulhu nechasim? So if you're saying fundamentally the sons and the
daughters are equal, why does the פסוק pasuk wouldn't have to say,
oh if there's you know if there's only one child, the child
gets it all. Meaning what you need to tell me is sons
and daughters are equal. We'll figure out the rest on myself. But
why would you have to say if saying if there's no son
it goes to the daughter is just as much as saying if
there's not child A but there's child B then child B gets
it. Of course that's true, right? If there's no priority of son
and daughter, why do you have to tell me if you don't
have a child number one but you have child number two then
child number two is going to get it? Of course it's true.
So אלא ודילמא הכא קמ"ל, ella v'dilma hacha k'masla, no no no,
maybe here's the point of the פסוק. pasuk. דבת נמי בת ירושה
היא. debas nami bas yerusha hi. Maybe the פסוק pasuk is telling
me it has to tell me explicitly daughter because otherwise I would
have said even if the פסוק pasuk had said if a person
dies you pass over his inheritance to his children. I would have
interpreted children to mean sons. I would have just assumed that of
course we're only talking about the sons. So the פסוק pasuk has
to explicitly say that a daughter also inherits. But maybe after it
explicitly says that a daughter inherits, והעברתם את נחלתו לבתו, ve-ha'avartem es
nachalaso levito, what I should learn from that is that she inherits
equal to the son. Of course, it's still a very funny way
to write the פסוק. pasuk. Right? The פסוק pasuk said, it should
have said, if a person dies, you should give his נחלה nachalah
to his sons and daughters. Right? It's still a funny way of
saying, you know, if there's no son, his daughter gets it, which
makes it very clear she's second in line. But the גמרא Gemara
is saying, no, prove that for me. I'll still argue that it
had to say daughter explicitly to know that a daughter can inherit.
But once it tells me that, maybe daughters and sons are equal.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, you don't need that פסוק pasuk
to tell you daughters inherit. The גמרא Gemara says ההיא מכל בת
יורשת נחלה נפקא, hahi mi-kol bas yoreshes nachalah nafka, because another פסוק
pasuk says every daughter who inherits, who receives an inheritance. So once
it's already clear that daughters are in the, can receive an inheritance
after בנות צלפחד Bnos Tzelofchad made their whole, you know, plea or
whatever, once it's clear that a daughter receives it, the פסוק pasuk
should have just said according to you, if a person dies, you
give it to his children. And then I would have known it
meant sons and daughters, once I've introduced the idea that daughters get
it. Since it doesn't say that, it says if he dies and
there're no sons, you give it to the daughter, it's very clear
that the sons get first. I guess this is a very convoluted
way of just getting to the פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk.
But the גמרא Gemara is just saying like what, you know, how
is it absolutely clear in the פסוקים pesukim that that's what it
means? Yes, Jenna.
So it says a פסוק pasuk that already tells us that daughters
inherit. What's the point of this פסוק, pasuk, to tell us the
order?
Yes, exactly. Daughter, right, so, you know, exactly, that once you know
daughters inherit, maybe they're equal to sons. Now this makes it clear,
no, only in the absence of sons. Yes.
So if there's no children?
Then it goes to the brother. And then it goes to the
father and after the father to the brother. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So רב אחא בר
יעקב אמר מהכא. Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar mehacha. למה יגרע, lama
yigara, so that's one proof that the daughters are in the line
and get it, and once daughters are getting, the פסוק pasuk of
if there's no son it gives it to daughters is very explicit
that they get it at the second level, not at the first
level. So now רב אחא בר יעקב אמר מהכא, Rav Acha bar
Yaakov amar mehacha, no, no, we know daughters get it, not from
the פסוק pasuk of וכל בת יורשת נחלה, ve-chol bas yoreshes nachalah,
but we know it or we know it like, or I'm sorry,
we know that daughters get and they get after the sons
implicitly from
the plea of בנות צלפחד, Bnos Tzelofchad, because here's what בנות צלפחד
Bnos Tzelofchad said. למה יגרע שם אבינו מתוך משפחתו כי אין לו
בן? lama yigara shem avinu mi-toch mishpachto ki ein lo ben? Why
should our father's name be lost from the family just because he
has no son? תנה לנו אחוזה בתוך אחי אבינו, tenah lanu achuzah
be-toch achei avinu, give us an inheritance. So meaning, implicitly they're saying,
we would not be here if our father had sons. We'd be
okay that the sons would get it. The reason we're here is
there are no sons and therefore in the absence of sons we
should be entitled. So that whole structure makes it clear that what,
that the daughters are coming in in the absence of sons. So
the גמרא Gemara says טעמא דאין לו בן. ta'ama de-ein lo ben.
The reason they're making their claim is because there are no sons.
הא יש לו בן, ha yesh lo ben, if the father had
a son, בן קודם, ben kodem, they would have accepted the son
comes first. So clearly, son comes before daughter. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, you can't prove it from that. ודילמא בנות צלפחד הוא
דקא אמרי הכי. u-dilma Bnos Tzelofchad hu de-ka amri hachi. That's what
בנות צלפחד Bnos Tzelofchad said. They were prepared to accept getting it
after the sons. They were saying we'd get if there were sons
they would come first, but if there're no sons we should get.
But maybe when God responded, God gave them more than they, you
know, changed the law more drastically than they were even asking for.
Okay? ונתנה תורה ונתחדשה הלכה. ve-nitnah Torah ve-nis'chadshah halachah. Maybe once the
Torah was given, it was like, you're only asking to get after
the sons. I'm going to tell you that now the daughters get
together with the sons. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara is imagining a
possibility of a very egalitarian response from God to their claim. At
least that's a הוה אמינא. hava amina. So that's why you can't
prove from what they were saying what the answer is. Okay? And
therefore we have to prove from not from their claim, but from
the פסוקים pesukim after their claim that that structure still remains, first
son and then daughter. אלא מחוורתא כדשנין מעיקרא. ela michvarta ki-deshanin me-ikara.
It's better like we said earlier, that it's not from the way
they're claiming it or what they're asking for, but it's what then
God responded that also is clear that it retains that order. כי
אין בן, ki ein ben, only when there's no son, then והעברתם
את נחלתו לבתו. ve-ha'avartem es nachalaso levito. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. רבינא אמר מהכא. Ravina amar mehacha. רבינא Ravina
says no, I will tell you that a son comes first from
the following, from the following פסוק. pasuk. It's so funny we're working
so hard to say what's פשט pshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. But
okay. I will tell you from the following פסוק. pasuk.
הקרוב אליו. ha-karov eilav. So I can't take the question. Okay. We'll
talk afterwards. It says הקרוב אליו. ha-karov eilav. So it
says ונתתם את נחלתו לשארו הקרוב אליו ממשפחתו. u-nesatem es nachalaso li-sh'eiro
ha-karov eilav mi-mishpachto. לשארו הקרוב אליו ממשפחתו, li-sh'eiro ha-karov eilav mi-mishpachto, right?
So the one closest to him from his family, הקרוב אליו. ha-karov
eilav. הקרוב קרוב קודם, HaKarov Karov Kodem, which we said this before.
The earlier, the closer you are in relationship, the earlier you are,
the, you know, the higher up you are to inherit. So therefore,
we should just infer from that that sons come before daughters. So
how do we know that? ומאי קורבא דבן מבת? U'mai kurva de-ben
mi-bas? How do we know that the son is closer than the
daughter? Okay, which is like now even if we know the הלכה,
Halacha, this is an important discussion in the גמרא Gemara because the
גמרא Gemara because it sort of reflecting where do we see in
general that logic that, you know, the son is, you know, considered
a closer relationship than the daughter. So where do we see that?
So the גמרא Gemara says again, that's obviously a factor of the
patriarchy, but let's see. The גמרא Gemara says like this, obviously doesn't
mean just, you know, biologically close, it means family structurally closer.
ומאי קורבא דבן מבת? U'mai kurva de-ben mi-bas? שבן קם תחת אביו
ליעדה ולשדה אחוזה. She-ben kam tachas aviv le-ye'adah u-l'sedei achuzah. We see
this elsewhere that the son is seen as a continuation of the
father in a way the daughter is not. Where do you see
a son is a continuation of the father? First of all, if
the father takes a Hebrew maidservant, then he, the father can marry
and if the father doesn't marry, the son can marry. So the
son is sort of playing the father's role. And if the father
sanctifies a field and the son redeems it, it's like the father
redeems it and it doesn't go out to the כהנים Kohanim in
the יובל. Yovel. This doesn't apply if the daughter redeems it. So
okay, so right, that obviously is going to be the question. But
anyway, but now we're saying in those two areas you see a
role that the son plays as an extension of the father which
the daughter does not play. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
that's not a proof. First of all, בת לאו בת ייעוד היא.
Bas lav bas yi'ud hi. First of all, marrying the maidservant is
not an option for the daughter. Okay. So therefore, the גמרא Gemara
says that it's not a what do you call it, it's not,
you know, it doesn't prove that she doesn't play the same role,
it's just that this particular role is not meaning, this particular application
is not meaningful for her. שדה אחוזה נמי מהאי פירכא גופיה הוא
דהא קיימא לן. Sedei achuzah nami me-hai pircha gufeih hu de-ha kayma
lan. How do you know like Michael said, how do you know
that a daughter doesn't redeem a שדה אחוזה Sedei achuzah like the
son? The only reason we know it is because we know from
elsewhere that we assume a son is earlier than a daughter. So
you have to first give me that other place that proves a
son is earlier than a daughter. Because there's nothing in the פסוקים
Psukim that say only a son redeems a שדה אחוזה Sedei achuzah
not a daughter. דהא קיימא לן לתנא כלום יש יבום אלא במקום
שאין בן. De-ha kayma lan le-sana klum yesh yibum ela be-makom she-ein
ben.
Where do we know that a son has a close relation to
the father and therefore is seen as the one to redeem the
שדה אחוזה? Sedei achuzah? It's because the גמרא Gemara says because he's
closer than the brother. How do you know he's closer than a
brother? Because when there's a son, there's no יבום. Yibum. So clearly
that proves...
right. So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. If that
proves that a son is closer than a brother and that the
son is the one who redeems the שדה אחוזה, Sedei achuzah, well
the same is true about a daughter. If there's a daughter, there's
no יבום. Yibum. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא במקום שאין
בן ela be-makom she-ein ben and that would apply as well to
a daughter. So therefore,
A, ייעוד yi'ud is not relevant to a daughter. B, שדה אחוזה
sedei achuzah for all we know could apply to a daughter as
well, unless you prove me from somewhere else that a daughter is
less close than the son. אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא. Ela mechuverta kideshaninan
mei-ikara. At the end of the day, we don't know it from
elsewhere. This is really fascinating. We don't know from anywhere else that
a son is closer than the daughter. So we cannot prove from
הקרוב קרוב קודם. ha-karov karov kodem. The only place we know, the
גמרא's Gemara saying right now, that a son is seen as closer
in the family structure is based on the idea of what do
you call it, is based on the fact that he inherits first.
And that it says, you know, אם אין לו בן והעברתם את
נחלתו לבתו. im ein lo ben ve-ha'avartem es nachalaso le-viso. You have
to learn it from that פסוק. Pasuk. You can't learn it from
a general idea that the son is higher in the hierarchy because
we don't know that from anywhere else. This becomes the basis that
the son is seen as higher in the family structure because he
is the first heir from the פסוק Pasuk of אם אין לו
בן. im ein lo ben. Of course you could say what about
the fact that the father can like, you know, marry off his
daughter, sell his daughter as a maidservant? Doesn't that show that she's
not exactly in the same place in the family as the son?
But interesting, closer that he can sell her. He has more control
over her, right? Yes.
Does that even apply if the son is two years old and
the daughter's 15?
Absolutely. Yes, exactly. Think about the English monarchy, right? So right, you're
going to have all these adult daughters and a one day old
baby son and the son would become the king. Alright, so okay.
So the גמרא Gemara אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא. ela mechuverta kideshaninan mei-ikara.
ואי בעית אימא מהכא. Ve-i bayis eima me-hacha. Oh,
here's another פסוק Pasuk which says that the son comes first. והתנחלתם
אותם לבניכם אחריכם. Ve-hisnachaltem osam li-vneichem achareichem.
You shall bequeath them, which is again by inheritance. Okay, but slaves.
But again the where we see the son is... Primary is, you
shall bequeath your slaves לבניכם אחריכם, livneichem achareichem, to your sons after
you. So there you see sons rather than daughters. So the גמרא
Gemara says, one minute, בניכם bneichem does not necessarily mean sons. בניכם
bneichem especially in the plural or whatever can mean children. So the
גמרא Gemara says, בניכם ולא בנותיכם. bneichem velo bnoseichem. אלא מעתה, ela
me'ata, למען ירבו ימיכם וימי בניכם, leman yirbu yemeichem vimei vneichem, in
order that it should increase your days and the days of your
children, הכא נמי hacha nami בניכם ולא בנותיכם? bneichem velo bnoseichem? So
do you mean that means to say that we're not making any
promises about your daughters? Only your sons' lives will increase? So גמרא
Gemara says, no, ברכה שאני. bracha shani.
Certainly we assume, thank you, that in the context of a blessing
the word בן ben is meant in its more expansive form of
children. Why should daughters be excluded from the blessing? But you know,
but otherwise we might assume that the word בן ben means
narrowly son and not daughter. It's an interesting question. What is our
default of interpreting the word בניכם? bneichem? Is our default to say
it means son unless somehow the context pushes us to say that
it means daughters, or is our default to say it means, thank
you, children unless there's some indication that it means sons? The גמרא
Gemara makes it sound like our default is sons, unless something like
the fact that we're talking about a ברכה bracha so obviously that
would be more global pushes us to say it means children. This
also comes up in the מצוה mitzvah of תלמוד תורה. talmud torah.
והלמדתם אותם את בניכם לדבר בם, velimadetem otam es bneichem ledaber bam,
בניכם ולא בנותיכם, bneichem velo bnoseichem, right?
Why should I interpret בניכם bneichem to mean sons? Why don't I
interpret בניכם bneichem to mean children, right? You know, ארבעה בנים arba
banim we just had on פסח, Pesach, right? Four sons or four
children, right? Some modern הגדות Haggadot translate it as four children, right?
But anyway, but that's different because when it says בן ben in
the singular there's probably more reason to assume it means son, but
בניכם bneichem in the plural since anyway a collection of boys and
girls, of men and women, would use the male plural pronoun, right?
So you could easily could mean children, but here it's sort of
saying the default is that it means sons. Somebody actually told me
in modern Hebrew, I don't know, or in some places in Israel
they're coming up, you know about this, they're coming up with a
new plural, like if a teacher wants to speak to a class
of boys and girls they'll say
תלמידותים. talmidotim.
Not תלמידים talmidim and not תלמידות, talmidot, תלמידותים. talmidotim. Okay, to have
both of them. But anyway, yes.
Just so to understand, so the reason why we're able to say
בניכם, bneichem, we do say בניכם ולא בנותיכם bneichem velo bnoseichem is
because that is not the ברכה, bracha, right?
Only the ברכה bracha is where the default is בניכם bneichem means
sons except in a clear context in which it's meant to be
more inclusive. Okay let's just begin the next one, see if we
can get to the bottom of the דף. daf. Okay, ואחי מן
האב נוחלין ומנחילין. ve'achi min ha'av nochalin umanchilin. Brothers of a same
father inherit from one another. Now again we've already established son, then
daughter, then father, then brother, right? So we've already established that. So
we don't have to prove that brother is next, that we're now
good. We got son and then daughter, that's what we just did.
We did father before brother, that's what we did yesterday. So now
brother. So now the only thing that we have to establish though
is that it's defined only as a brother with a paternal brother,
not a maternal, אחי מן האב. achi min ha'av.
So מנלן, menalan, how do you know that brothers are only defined
as paternal? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, אתיא אח אח מבני יעקב.
atya ach ach mivnei Yaakov. We learn it out from the sons
of יעקב. Yaakov. They say כולנו בני איש אחד אנחנו, kulanu bnei
ish echad anachnu, right? We're all, I mean, they all are whatever,
you know, and they were all אחים. achim. So there's a פסוק
pasuk there which somewhere here, what's the פסוק? pasuk? שנים
עשר עבדיך אחים אנחנו בני איש אחד. shneim asar avadecha achim anachnu
bnei ish echad. So it says very right, אחים אנחנו בני איש
אחד. achim anachnu bnei ish echad. So you see brothers are defined
by a same father. מה להלן מן האב ולא מן האם אף
כאן מן האב ולא מן האם. ma lehalan min ha'av velo min
ha'em af kan min ha'av velo min ha'em. So the גמרא Gemara
says, למה לי, lama li, why do I need to go to
בני יעקב? bnei Yaakov? ממשפחתו ירש אותה. mimeshpachto yerash osah. Once again,
let's just go by our default rule that it goes by patriarchal
structure. The family is defined through the father.
משפחת אב קרויה משפחה משפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה, mishpachat av kruya
mishpacha mishpachat em eina kruya mishpacha, right? That's very, like that's important.
That is the underpinning assumption here, right? The family structure is defined
by the
father, so obviously brothers are brothers of a same father. That is
the same family. So אי הכי נמי, in hachi nami, you're right,
you don't need to go to יעקב, Yaakov, you just know it
from the general rule that we're dealing with a patriarchal structure. וכי
איתמר דרבא, vechi itmar de'Rava, so why do you need רבא Rava
to tell you the idea of brothers by default means brothers through
a same father? ביבום איתמר. biyibum itmar. By יבום, yibum, because by
יבום yibum it says right that the אח ach does יבום. yibum.
איש כי ימות ובן אין לו, ish ki yamut uven ein lo,
what does it say? No, I'm quoting the other book. כי ישבו
אחים יחדיו ומת אחד מהם
ובן אין לו.
ki yeshvu achim yachdav umes echad mehem
uven ein lo. לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר יבמה יבוא
עליה. lo sihye eshas hames hachutza le'ish zar yevama yavo aleha. Anyway,
but okay, but כי ישבו אחים יחדיו. ki yeshvu achim yachdav. Okay
when brothers sit together. So there since it's not in the context
of directly in the context of inheritance and it's not directly in
the context
of... Which by the way makes sense, cause it's all about שם
אחיו shem achiv and it's really about family name and so on.
So obviously that really is a part of that, but it's not
as explicit. Okay, but once again we're going back to the idea
of the patriarchal and the defined through the father's family.